Guide to the Lillian Picken Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Lillian Picken Papers
1921-1974
RG 159
Yale University Divinity School Library
4.5
(12 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, and collected materials document Picken's work and the work of the ABCFM in India beginning in 1928. Lillian Picken was an American missionary in India, serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, American Marathi Mission, later known as the United Church Board for World Ministries. She took part in educational, industrial, social, and evangelistic work in the Satara area of western India.
Picken, Lillian
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from New York offices of United Church Board for World Ministries, 2000.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Lillian Picken was born in Eureka, Kansas and graduated from Kansas State Teachers College (1908) and Colorado College (1912). She was assigned to Bombay when she first went to India under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions in 1914, but transferred to the Satara area in 1919, where she engaged in educational, industrial, social, and evangelistic work. She founded the Child Welfare Center in Waduth, the Spiritual Life Center at Nasrapur, and an inter-denominational welfare center at Satara. With her close colleague Louise Fisher she founded the Rural Roadside Leprosy Control Clinic in 1954. Picken retired in 1957.
Scope and Contents
These papers provide valuable documentation of the work of an American woman missionary in western India. With her colleague Louise Fisher, Picken became deeply involved in social welfare, as well as evangelistic work, in the Indian villages where she served.
Series I, Correspondence of Lillian Picken, contains a long run of circular letters to Picken's supporters, which provide excellent detail regarding her missionary work. These letters are complemented by more personal correspondence, primarily with mission and Indian colleagues and friends. Picken maintained correspondence with Indian colleagues, particular her "adopted son" Sumitra Palve after her retirement. Series II, Correspondence of Others, contains a run of circular letters from Picken's colleague Lousie Fisher that supplements the documentation in Picken's correspondence, since they worked together closely.
Series III, Writings, includes writings of Picken on spiritual and mission topics as well as writings of others, mostly mission colleagues. The Notes of Series IV are primarily for Bible studies or talks that Picken gave while in the United States on furlough or after her retirement.
Series V, Subject File, contains material about the work of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions in Satara, the Navraspur Spiritual Life Center, leprosy work, the Dohnavur Fellowship and Indian Girl Guides. Two notebooks provide extensive information about the Satara misison. In combination with annual reports and periodicals of the ABCFM, this material would provide valuable documentation of the character of mission work in this area, and the lives of the missionaries involved.
Series VI, Personal Items and Memorabilia, contains biographical documentation, documentation of Picken's speaking engagements, and various collected printed material of an inspirational character. Series VII, Photographs, includes photographs of Picken, Louise Fisher, Indian colleagues, etc.
Series VII includes Photographs and Slides of Lillian Picken and her colleagues as well as of the Nasrapur Spiritual Life Center, and other scenes in India.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence of Lillian Picken
II. Correspondence of Others
III. Writings
IV. Notes
V. Subject File
VI. Personal Items and Memorabilia
VII. Photographs and Slides
Missions -- India; Rural development -- Religious aspects -- Christianity; Missionaries; Fisher, Louise; Picken, Lillian; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions -- Missions -- India
- Correspondence of Lillian Picken, Series I
  - Circular letters to supporters
    - Letters, 1922 -1968 (Box 1, Folder 1-18)
    - Fragments (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence with family and friends
    - To/from family and friends, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
    - From Louise Fisher, 1947-1966, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Early family corres., 1921, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence with others
    - A - B (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Bhonsle, P. S. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Crozier, Mr. and Mrs. John (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - C - D (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Dudley, Raymond A. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - E - K (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Kehinde, Wande (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Laubach, Frank (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - M - N (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Ng, Wai Yee (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Packard, Frank (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Palve, Sumitra (corres. in subject file) (Box 4, Folder 75-77)
    - Pandit, S. R. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Manorama Powar (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Rotary Club (incl. letters from J. C. Penney) (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - R - S (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - T - W, unidentified (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Westchester churches (supporting Picken) (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Correspondence of Others, Series II
  - Louise Fisher to supporters (circular letters), 1936-1970 (Box 3, Folder 41-45)
  - Lousie Fisher - personal correspondence, 1947-1959 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Frank Packard letters (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Writings, Series III
  - By Lillian Picken
    - Published material
      - Prayer, Bible study outline (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Typescript material
      - Re. India: "India's Quest", "The Indigenous Church in India", etc. (Box 3, Folder 49)
      - Bible studies: "How much do I love my church?", 1947 Jun (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - Bible studies: "Victorious life in Jesus Christ", 1935-1936 (Box 3, Folder 51)
      - Paper: "The meaning of the Holy Spirit for today", 1954 Apr (Box 3, Folder 52)
      - Paper: "The relevance of the Trinity", 1954 Apr (Box 3, Folder 53)
      - Paper: "The healing ministry of Jesus", 1954 May (Box 3, Folder 54)
      - Paper: "My reactions to the following feet - Ancilla", 1954 May (Box 3, Folder 55)
      - Paper: "The Christian faith in life everlasting", 1954 May (Box 3, Folder 55a)
  - Writings of others
    - A - K (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - L - S (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - T - W (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Unidentified (Box 3, Folder 59)
- Notes, Series IV
  - LP: Personal Bible studies (Box 4, Folder 60-62)
  - LP: Notes for talks (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - LP: Notes from retreats, 1938-1958, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 64-68)
  - Notes of others (Box 4, Folder 69)
- Subject File, Series V
  - ABCFM/ American Marathi Mission in India
    - Satara Mission (Box 4, Folder 70, 71)
    - Satara Mission, leprosy work (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Satara Mission - two notebooks of history compiled by Louise Fisher (Box 7, Folder 101, 102)
    - Vadala Mission (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Vadala - Sumitra Palve - Director of agricultural work, 1963-1974 (Box 4, Folder 74-77)
    - Nasrapur Spiritual Life Center, 1958-1962 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - India
    - Dohnavur Fellowship (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - Indian Girl Guides (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - News items (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - Indian religions (Box 7, Folder 106-108)
  - Miscellaneous
    - East Africa revival, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Sahel Famine, West Africa - Lady Bug project, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 80, 81)
    - News excerpts, reports, Fellowship of the Least Coin, etc. (Box 5, Folder 82)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series VI
  - Material re. healing ministries (Box 5, Folder 83, 84a)
  - Fisher - Picken financial records (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Biographical documentation (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Poems, quotations, tributes (Box 5, Folder 86, 86a, 87)
  - Programmes and pamphlets (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Info. re. speaking engagements (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Miscellaneous memorabilia, incl. personal New Testament and Ink/stamp set (Box 6, Folder 90, 91)
  - Miscellaneous diplomas and documents (Box 12)
- Photographs and Slides, Series VII
  - Lillian Picken (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Lillian Picken with others (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Louise Fisher (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Sumitra Palve (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Wai Yee Ng (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Various individuals (Box 6, Folder 97-99)
  - Scenes and sketches (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - FEAD Centre (women sewing, making baskets); Osmanabad Vikas Karya; Satara, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Slides: Box 1: Fatepursikri and Delhi (Box 8)
  - Slides: Box 2: Vadala? (Box 8)
  - Slides: Box 3: Unidentified - India - groups (Box 8)
  - Slides: Box 4: Nasrapur (Box 8)
  - Slides: Box 5: Nasrapur - individuals and gorups (Box 9)
  - Slides: Box 6: Nasrapur - inc. Bishop Newbigin, Dr. Laubach (Box 9)
  - Slides: Box 7: Nasrapur Spiritual Life Center: camps, conferences (Box 9)
  - Slides: Box 8: Lillian Picken, groups, scenery (Box 9)
  - Slides: Box 9: South India temples, Nasrapur (Box 9)
  - Slides: Box 10: Taj Mahal (Box 9)
  - Slides: Box 11: Agriculture, primitive homes (Box 9)
  - Slides: Box 12: Satara (Box 10)
  - Slides: Box 13: Satara (Box 10)
  - Slides: Box 14: Satara (Box 10)
  - Slides: Box 15: Satara, with accompanying pages of identification (Box 10)
  - Slides: Box 16: Hawaii, Grand Canyon (Box 11)
  - Slides: Box 17: Honolulu, Hawaii (Box 11)
  - Slides: Box 18: Travel in U.S. (Box 11)